[Music]
welcome to another episode of
overrated underrated now i posted one of
these videos a couple weeks ago it was a
big hit so
we're at it again with episode number
two so today's topic
is on glute training by big booty
influencers now as always i've got alex
with me he's gonna roll off the
questions
and i will tell you whether i think it's
overrated or underrated and
offer my explanation okay alex what's
first
squeezing glutes at the top of a squat
so this is a very common question i get
people want to know my thoughts on the
topic and it's it's crazy it's a very
volatile topic in this industry
like power lifters they get so mad when
they see squeezing the glutes at the top
of a squat
it's like very offensive like it like
activates this visceral
rage and here's my take i see no problem
with it now i wrote about this in glute
lab
in theory if you squeeze the glutes too
hard and post your pelvic tilt too much
you know like he's totally tucked under
and you know you look like a dog going
to the bathroom because you post your
pelvic tilted so much
then you're increasing injury risk to
the lumbar spine
same thing if you just push the hips
forward too much by squeezing glutes and
you hyperextend
that also increases injury risk to the
lumbar spine but as long as you don't
overdo it you just squeeze the glutes
it's fine
and it could actually be beneficial and
here's why i used to train at this power
lifting gym
in tempe back when i lived in scottsdale
it was called
revolution training and there were some
really strong people there but a couple
of the lifters
would squeeze their glutes really hard
and then descend into the squat
in fact one got red lighted for it and
the judge told him you can't have any
counter movement
squeeze the glutes but don't move don't
have any movement associated with it but
i always try to think why does he do
that
you know does it help him and
theoretically
it could offer some sort of post
activation potentiation benefit
maybe by squeezing the glutes really
hard then descending into the squat
maybe somehow they're potentiated and
you end up using them more
out of the hole i mean who knows this
was like five years ago a lot of people
were doing a lot of power lifters were
doing it
and then the trend kind of faded off so
i'd like to see these same dudes yell at
the power lifters when they used to do
that
these were some strong dudes i don't
think anyone would talk smack but when
the
females do it it's enraging now in a
recent video i just made on band
pronounced i mentioned my
my buddy jam aaron he used to have all
his girls squeeze their glutes
on everything on the top of a squat the
top of a deadlift
freaking every movement they would do
they'd squeeze their glutes and here's
the deal he trained a ton
of like top 10 bikini olympians he
trained a lot of
high level women and some of them had
radical glute transformation so you're
going to tell him he was doing it wrong
maybe he was doing it just right and we
should all take notes now i don't have
my clients squeeze their glutes at the
top of a squat
because i have them hip thrusting all
the time and they're always squeezing
their glutes at the top of a hip thrust
so i just say focus on squeezing your
glutes during exercise that are the
hardest at lockout
not exercises that are hardest at the
bottom for example
at the top of a squat and a lunge it's
unnecessary the glutes are kind of
unloaded at lock out
they're needed as you go deep they're
not needed at the top
so the glute squeeze could just be
irrelevant nevertheless it's not going
to hurt anyone
if you want to squeeze your glutes at
the top of the squat go for it this is
going to piss some people off but i'm
going to go with
underrated hovering off the seat during
seated hip abductions
all right chances are you've seen this
on social media and
i don't think i've ever seen i've seen a
guy do it but you do see this with a lot
of the
female influencers you'll see them doing
seated hip abductions
but they're hovering they're not sitting
on the seat they're kind of in a squat
in fact now a couple of manufacturers
have caught onto this
and they offer hip abduction machines
with no seed
so you have to hover now in theory this
is going to increase glute activation
because you're kind of like
squatting and doing abductions at the
same exact time
and some of my clients like it more like
my client lorita
that's her preferred way of doing them i
tried it that way and i didn't like it i
like just sitting on the seat more
and there's lots of options you can lean
back you can be straight up you can lean
forward
we do triple drop sets we do enhanced
eccentrics off the seated hip production
machine
so i just see the hover method as a
viable
variation that you can do and i see
nothing wrong with it give it a try
see if you like it i see the bros
bashing this movement and i don't see
why
i say underrated two thumbs up step
downs
off the chin or dip station step downs
of the chin up dip station
now this you've probably seen in the gym
you're wondering why is she using it you
want to use the chin up dip station for
assisted chin ups or dips and there's
some booty influencer
on there using it to perform step downs
she's pushing her leg down
i thought this was the dumbest looking
exercise i thought what a waste of time
you know it's not going to be as
effective as step ups step ups are a
closed chain exercise these step downs
would be an open chain exercise
if you're fit you're probably not going
to be able to use enough weight for it
to be effective
but i actually gave this a try and i was
wrong
i love these i thought i'd hate them but
especially if you get good at them
you're getting a little groove
you will feel it working that glute step
downs off the assisted chin up station
underrated sideline single leg leg press
all right you you have to have seen this
in the gym too
and again i i i don't see bros doing
this bros stick to the basics you'll see
a lot of
booty influencers they turn their body
to the side and they do the
the leg press the single leg leg press
but they're turned to the side
now i thought this was so stupid too i'd
look at anybody like
why in the hell would they do that but i
gave this a try too
and guess what i liked it it's hard for
me to get into position because i'm just
a big
oaf but off the unit i use it was kind
of nice because
it's like i had to abduct as i came up
it felt like it was a unique path and i
felt it in my glute a little bit more
now i'm gonna still stick to just your
regular single leg leg press
facing forward but if you try side lying
and you like it more stick with it i say
underrated racing the non-working leg
during step-ups all right
raising the non-working leg during step
up so you'll see this all the time
uh you see bros and women doing this
they're doing a step
up and when they get to the top they
lift the other leg up
into like a high knee raise now this
isn't necessarily increasing the work on
the opposite glute and they think it is
i
i know they think it's like working the
glute harder all you're really doing
is working that hip flexor you know
you're doing a leg raise
to work the opposite hip flexor but i
actually like this tactic
and here's why one of the ways that
people cheat during a high step
up is they kind of propel themselves up
giving themselves a momentum
and then they catch themselves before
they lock it out they catch themselves
with the non-working leg and then they
stand up like a little quarter squat
so by not touching down and raising the
leg
you make sure that all the work is done
on that one leg and you don't end up
catching yourself at the top and making
it kind of like a
bilateral movement it's all unilateral
you're all on one leg so i'm going to
give it
underrated kickbacks off the smith
machine okay i actually just posted a
video
using the smith machine last week one of
the exercises we showcased was kickbacks
we also had like the frog kickback in
there
this could be included in that i don't
like these
i don't like them much i just can't get
into them they don't feel right for me
but i think it's really important
as a trainer to talk to clients talk to
other lifters have a
have a big network don't just judge your
entire opinion of an exercise based on
how you feel because you might have a
unique anatomy
that causes you to really like an
exercise or really dislike an exercise
and you may not conform to the masses
very well and some of my clients really
like these kickbacks so they're not that
popular i would say
properly rated it thrust off the leg
curl machine hip dust off the leg chrome
machine
when i first saw these i thought they
were so dumb you know how are you gonna
even have enough weight
how are you gonna have enough resistance
you put on the stack is that gonna be
enough you know i have some of my
clients hip dusting five
six even 700 pounds how is a 200 pound
stack gonna give them ample resistance
but i actually gave it a try and
boy is it smooth the resistance curve is
just nice and smooth
so if you're a beginner you can
definitely use it and even if you're
advanced
you go nice and controlled do a pause if
it's too tall for you
put your feet on a step so you can use
more range of motion
but they felt good if you do them for
high reps with little paws at the top
you will feel your glutes burning big
time
these are underrated kickbacks during
the step mill
kickbacks during the stepmill now you
see this all the time someone's using
the stepmill
for cardio and each time they step they
take a step forward
they step up and as they step up they
kick back with the opposite leg
and in theory you're going they're just
doing a bodyweight kickback how could
this be effective but
like i said with squeezing the glutes at
the top of a squat i mean is it hurting
anyone
now you could say there's no resistance
it's just a bodyweight kickback but
if they squeeze hard maybe they develop
some tension in there
and maybe there's some sort of post
activation potentiation effect where you
end up using your glutes more during the
actual step
up process so a case could be made
whether they're good or bad
but i'm gonna go ahead and rate this
overrated mini bands during the
stairmaster
mini bands during the stairmaster so uh
you can kind of
just say mini bands throughout life
you'll see people wearing mini bands all
the time during different exercises
but yeah you see them during the step
mill and
uh you might think uh that's no big deal
but it makes it so much harder
like after a few minutes you're dying i
mean you just just put the mini bands
around your knees and just
hang out for a while just you know walk
and get a drink walk back
walk around doing exercises and you'll
start feeling the glutes burning like
crazy
so yes it makes you feel your glutes
more but i think it's just it's constant
it's relentless it's aerobic
it's not anaerobic i don't think it
builds the glutes
overrated squatting during lateral
bandwalks
squatting during lateral bandwalks i
prefer doing lateral bandwalks upright
and this is going to target the upper
glutes more when you do them real
squatty
that's a different type of movement and
i like using bands to target the upper
glutes most of the time
not necessarily trying to do squatting
motions with it or make it harder
so if you do this as a variation that's
totally fine
but most the time i do want you more in
the frontal plane more upright so i'm
gonna go with
overrated lateral lunge off the bosu
ball
okay picture this you're standing on the
bosu ball
you know dome facing up and you do a
lateral lunge off of it
and the theory is because it's unstable
the glute's gonna work harder as a
stabilizer
guess what here's the deal you actually
work your glutes harder if you stood on
flat ground
on a stable surface and actually use
dumbbells with it there are some
situations
where unstable surface training might be
beneficial but not when you're trying to
grow your glutes
keep it stable overrated circuit
training for
glutes circuit training for glutes let
me tell you a little story when i first
started glute lab san diego
my glute squat sessions were giant
circuits and the clients
loved them they were legendary i'd have
30 girls at a time there
a lot of them being bikini competitors
and they loved it their glutes were
burning
you got all the variety you wanted you
were sweating
heart rate going crazy and guess what it
didn't work that well
one day i was watching one of my clients
doing lunges off the lever squat machine
so doing lever reverse lunges
she stopped the set and i was like i bet
you she could have done 20 more i mean
bottom line she wasn't even going close
to failure so you're doing a hard
workout
in total but nothing's really that
challenging for the glutes this is
aerobic in nature aerobics don't build
the glutes cardio is not that good for
glute development
massively overrated for glutes band
burnouts for glutes interestingly i just
posted a video on this exact topic a
week ago
and i concluded that they are beneficial
but they have to be done a certain way
you don't do eight straight abduction
movements you're going to alternate
between
hip extension and hip abduction
movements when they're done that way and
you keep them to two to three minutes
they are underrated they work well plows
for glutes
plyos for glutes okay you see this all
the time and
you know it's not really plyos well
pliers are for athletes
and the goal is to increase your
explosive power the way most fitness
people do
plyos is really just jump conditioning
you're just doing
conditioning work with a lot of jumping
you're not increasing your power you're
just kind of increasing your power
endurance but you're definitely not
building the glutes
plyos are not as effective for glute
development as straight up weight
training
the tension is high but it's too fast
you need a longer contraction time
to develop maximum force in the muscle
therefore
they are overrated gimmicky gadgets
gimmicky gadgets for glutes obviously i
gave the answer away in the title
it's going to be overrated but i wanted
to name some examples of these i don't
even know the name of this thing
i bought it it's that glute lab it's
this little thing that you
squeeze your butt you put in between
your thighs you squeeze your butt
it didn't even work at all like me and
my clients all felt our glutes working
more when we just did it with bodyweight
only we just did
bodyweight glute squeezes when we didn't
have the contraption on this thing
looked cool
in theory but in reality it didn't pan
out another gadget i see lately is these
bfr
bands there's actually a study
supporting the bfr band but i'm still
not convinced i still see them as a
gadget i like blood flow restriction
training for the muscles distal to the
cuff like biceps triceps or quads and
hammies
just not glutes you can say this for all
the infomercial type products all these
electric muscle stimulation devices
and these crazy looking things that like
you squat on and it assists you with it
just squat or these glute bridge or hip
thrust machines that offer very little
resistance at the top they have crappy
bands that you only feel at the very
lockout
those don't work well save your money
overrated
combine movements the topic is combined
movements for glutes think of someone
doing like dumbbell reverse
lunge into a curl into a press back into
the lunge like all in one movement or
think of someone doing like a back
extension into a row
these are examples of combined movements
and i just think they're
so silly because yes it's cardio it's
gonna get you breathing hard
it's gonna get your heart rate up but
why not just do cardio or push a sled do
burpees do mountain climbers the point
is you're just burning calories you can
do anything to burn calories if that's
your goal
but if you're trying to build your
glutes you need to maximize tension on
the glutes
and you're going to be able to use more
weight for a lunge than a press so the
glutes get short changed your upper body
muscles will probably be the limiting
factor so then the glutes don't get
maximally challenging
you just get tired out without really
effectively working your glutes
overrated if you watch this video you
were probably
initially expecting me to bash all the
booty influencers and
and attack their methods but i actually
validated some of them and these
influencers have caused me to try some
things that i wouldn't have tried on my
own which i'm thankful for a good
scientist
is always skeptical but also open-minded
you gotta try things you gotta
experiment things
and form your own opinion but i think
some people like to hear what i have to
say because i have a phd and i've been
studying the glutes for so long
so it's always nice to hear a scientific
explanation all right that's a wrap
until next time i hope you enjoyed the
episode don't forget to hit like give it
a thumbs up
leave a comment if you want further
explanation and please make sure you're
subscribed to my channel i've got a lot
more to come in 2021
now if this video intrigued you and you
would like to train
under my system using my principles then
i invite you to click on the link below
and subscribe to booty by brett and join
the thousands of other happy members
who are seeing amazing results